IAN NELSON

50 Arundel Beach Rd., Severna Park MD, 21146

PHONE Please email for contact number

E-MAIL iannelson1@gmail.com



SUMMARY

Full-stack software engineer with over 20 years of development and analysis experience solving some of the nation's most difficult problems inside of the Intelligence Community, U.S. Military and private sector. I pride myself on work ethic, a consistent commitment to learning new technologies and am passionate about working on challenging problems with others.

SKILLS

- Eloquent writer, speaker and presenter.
- Quick to learn business processes, systems, and architectures in a new environment.
- Able to communicate effectively between business, technical, and sales staff members.
- Quick to provide training and mentorship to junior members of the team.
- Fluent and practiced in Agile/Scrum project methodologies (Certified ScrumMaster cert.)
- Able to participate as an individual team contributor or manage teams where needed.
- Practiced "outside the box" thinker.

SOFTWARE

JavaScript / Node.js HTML5 / Web Libs. Java Go Python Linux Systems / CLI Spark / Hadoop Ansible AWS / Cloud PaaS

Git + GitHub Workflow



EDUCATION

University of Maryland, University College

January 2010 - May 2012

B.S. in Computer Science

Adelphi, MD

• Nominated to Dean's List every enrolled semester, and invited to join Sigma Alpha Pi as an honor student. Graduated with Honors (Cum Laude, 3.75 GPA)

Arkansas Tech University

August 2007 - December 2008

B.S. in Computer Science

Russellville, AR

- Served as a team leader and university representative for Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) software development competitions.
- Also served as an official tutor for the Computer Science department, mentoring more than 30 students in basic and advanced computer science concepts, data structures, and principals of mathematical application.

EXPERIENCE

Coalition, Inc.

December 2021 to Present

Insurance Operations Strategist

San Francisco, CA (Remote)

- Migrated from Lead Principal Engineer to the Business unit to serve as the applied technologist for insurance relationships and operations
- Negotiated, closed and implemented ZenDesk and Salesforce FSC as MVP systems within the business unit. This included working with our Product organization to ensure proper systems integration with our insuretech was being considered
- Served as technical leadership for the Renewals program, including review of all quarterly work themes for Product/Engineering, development of SLAs and telemetry used to optimize team performance within ZenDesk, and development of target metrics for team hiring and scale during hyper-growth resulting in a total ROI during this period of \$250m / GWP
- Developed optimized process using technology for Customer Success organization, leading to base telemetry on inbound/outbound/performance for the first time in company history. Lead to consistent improvement in problem areas, fixing long standing issues with insurance brokers
- Worked with senior agency Cyber program leads to increase market penetration and adoption of Coalition policies and coverage across the industry
- Acted as company SME in applied security to act as a guide and resource for brokers, prospective policyholders, and internal employees to facilitate business opportunities
- Developed new and improved relationships between the corporation and US/UK Federal LEOs leading to better cooperation on cyber crimes, and improved financial recovery access for policyholders
- Served as liaison between security companies and vendors to improve Coalition underwriting and incident response capabilities through data access and services, including claims panel access

Coalition, Inc.

April 2018 to December 2021

Senior Principal Engineer

San Francisco, CA (Remote)

- Acted as lead principal engineer through three iterations of VP of Engineering, providing technical and business continuity
- Led company efforts in Customer Security Team, resulting in increased automation, consistency and improvement of loss ratio
- Developed scalable client security analysis service in parallel with business product team
- Worked with security engineers to help implement autonomous versions of tradecraft into development and production systems
- Worked with junior engineers to assist in technological design approaches and mentoring
- Implemented system queuing and task dispatch system using Apache NiFi. Later used as the baseline for further automated security improvements over the course of systems development
- Developed and sustained the automated renewals program from inception to modern day implementation, resulting in the development of an ROI worth \$100m's of GWP
- Worked as a technical lead for M&A activities during the acquisition of BinaryEdge, including eventual technical integration between both systems to facilitate and improve underwriting

- Developed in conjunction with VP of Engineering the current set of processes by which the
 department operates, including: team breakouts and assignment, architecture review
 documentation and review board, quarterly planning with agile sprint follow-on
- Served as the lead for the Engineering department's corps of principal engineers to facilitate discussions, agreed-upon solutions, and pathways for improvement in the production software and infrastructure

[redacted]

July 2016 to April 2018

Infrastructure Lead / SRE

Elkridge, MD + Remote Work

- Performed budgetary analysis and procurement execution of primary data center.
- Designed and implemented data center buildout, including system deployment, networking, and software implementation.
- Led effort to host and implement a JAMF instance to autonomously manage company iPhone and MBP fleet.
- Implemented program for vendor relationships with third-party where necessary.
- Helped to develop initial prototypes of analysis software for client research.
- Helped to support corporate operations team with subject matter expertise on client analysis as required.
- Designed and implemented continuous integration and deployment techniques for development team

IronNet Cybersecurity

October 2014 to July 2016

Senior Software Engineer

Fulton, MD

- Technical lead for streaming analytics effort. This product capability was implemented using data from a distributed Kafka bus to Spark Streaming. This architecture served as an interface to models performing unsupervised learning in near real-time.
- Served as the technical oversight staff member for the president of the company's Technical
 Division. This effort was critical in identifying technical issues during system and software
 integration as appliances were deployed into customer environments. In addition, worked with
 members of all component development teams and infrastructure personnel to adjust software
 design and implementation mechanics, ultimately leading to better continuous deployment.
- Designed and implemented several prototypes of a large-scale node graph visualization (100K+ nodes), giving full network situational awareness as a next-generation capability.
- Designed and implemented the first prototype and implementation of the product's user interface and RESTful API. Used a combination of AngularJS, Node.js, MongoDB and WebSockets to produce a fully streaming architecture to receive information and alerts from the product processing pipeline.

Clarity Innovations

June 2015 to August 2020

Member, Technical Advisory Board

Columbia, MD

- Assisted company executives in determining common technology trends to efficiently execute multiple contracts using a single development implementation.
- Worked with executive team to assist in contract acquisition and business analysis.

National Security Agency

April 2012 to October 2014

Technical Director

Fort Meade, MD

- Led three teams of 70+ software engineers developing OZONE Platform and the OZONE Widget Framework. This software was instrumental in government use by multiple agencies (Intelligence Community, U.S. Military, Social Security Administration, etc.) to conduct integration activities at a low-cost through an easy to use web application framework.
- Led the technical effort to implement the Intelligence Community (IC) Application Mall as part of
 the IC IT Enterprise activity to consolidate common infrastructure across agencies. Worked to
 solve elastic architectures needed to support Internet-scale user loads, and additionally worked
 with ODNI technical staff to ensure security mechanisms supported multi-agency access.
- Worked with network engineers to produce open-source prototype SDN controllers and enable collaboration between government, industry, and academic partners.

Akimeka

August 2011 to April 2012

Senior Technical Consultant

Honolulu. HI

- Served as a technical consultant to senior site personnel for visualization and web application development. Effort consisted of a triage to determine native (C++/Java) applications widely used by site personnel, determine the feasibility and level of effort required to transition as a web application, and work with teams to develop prototypes for testing.
- Led effort to develop a new HTML5 audio spectrum analyzer in ExtJS 4.x for use within the Ozone
 Widget Framework. This capability was used as the center point of audio processing workflows
 across various analysis threads.
- Led effort to design and prototype a geospatial analysis processing capability using Hadoop and Apache Accumulo. This effort was instrumental in correlating events to specific locations across a massive dataset within the cloud, with an aim to further enrich data processing capabilities across the site.